בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is מ"ו. mem vav. We're
a little behind, we better get caught up. So we're on the
first משנה mishna on מ"ה עמוד ב'. mem hey amud bet. Let's
take a look. There are two משניות, mishnayot, we're on the one
that is in the middle of the page. And yeah, let's get
going. So it's about עגלה, egla, we're dealing still with the process
of עגלה ערופה. Egla Arufa. So we have the בית דין beis
din representative of the בית דין הגדול beis din ha'gadol in ירושלים
Yerushalayim coming out and measuring to the nearby town or the most
nearby town that has a בית דין. beis din. And let's take
a look. נמצא מכוון בין שתי עיירות, Nimtza mechuvon bein shtei ayarot,
let's say the body is exactly equidistant between two towns.
שתיהן מביאות שתי עגלות דברי רבי אליעזר. Shteihen mevi'ot shtei agalot divrei
Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says they each bring an עגלה.
Egla. It's not they both bring two, but they each bring one.
Anyway, so the fact is that they both bring. I mean, the
whole point here is that it's a ספק. safek. So the fact
that it can't be from both of theirs, I mean, either way,
each one is doing it because of a ספק. safek. Okay, which
is interesting because you could have said that what they do is
that they, the בתי דין batei din of each town come together
and they bring one עגלה Egla and they stipulate, you know, if
it's closer to my town, then this is, you know, then this
is my עגלה. Egla. If it's closer to your town, then this
is your עגלה ערופה. Egla Arufa. But maybe it's not closer to
either guy, maybe it really is exactly equidistant.
Could be the order is one from each town.
Well, there's only one body. There's one body equidistant between two towns.
I see
for
the, there's,
we're not dealing with the case of yesterday of two bodies. There's
one body equidistant between two towns. Okay, so he says both בית,
beis, each בית דין beis din from each town brings an עגלה
ערופה. Egla Arufa. So we'll see that in the גמרא. gemara. That's
very, that's pretty strange. But what else are you supposed to do?
Okay, and now it doesn't give you, it's interesting, it says דברי
רבי אליעזר, divrei Rabbi Eliezer, it doesn't say what the other opinion
is. Sometimes you have that. You have the, clearly it's not unanimous,
but you don't know what the other side of it is. Okay,
then the משנה mishna continues ואין ירושלים מביאה עגלה ערופה. v'ein Yerushalayim
mevia Egla Arufa. If it's near ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you would not bring
an עגלה ערופה. Egla Arufa. נמצא ראשו במקום אחד וגופו במקום אחר,
Nimtza rosho b'makom echad v'gufo b'makom acher,
let's say the body's head has been severed and the head is
in one place and the body's in another place. מוליכין את הראש
אצל הגוף דברי רבי אליעזר. Molichin et harosh etzel haguf divrei Rabbi
Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you bring the head to the
body, which why you have to bring the head to the body,
but presumably you measure from the body. רבי עקיבא אומר הגוף אצל
הראש. Rabbi Akiva omer haguf etzel harosh. So you bring the body
to the head. Again, why you bring it is not clear, we'll
see in the גמרא, gemara, but presumably you measure from the head.
מאין היו מודדין, Me'ayin hayu modedin, except the end of the משנה
mishna asks the question from which part of the body you would
measure and it's not a question of head versus body. Let's take
a look. רבי אליעזר אומר מטיבורו Rabbi Eliezer omer mitiburo or well,
maybe it is, but said in a different way, from the belly
button. רבי עקיבא אומר מחוטמו, Rabbi Akiva omer mechotamo, from the nostrils.
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר ממקום שנעשה חלל, Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov
omer mimakom shena'asa chalal, the place where a person would become a
corpse or you know a חלל chalal is like a corpse slain
in war or whatever, which would be מצוארו. mitzavaro. So he understands
that the normal word of the word חלל chalal literally would relate
to normally a cutting off at the head, which actually fits into
the earlier scenario. Now is the question of bringing the head to
the body or the body to the head parallel to the question
of where you would measure it from? So if you take a
look, it actually is, looks to be somewhat parallel because רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer he says you bring the head to the body, says
you measure from the belly button and רבי, Rabbi, right, so that
makes the body the center place you measure from. And רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva that says you bring the body to the head, okay,
which means that says you measure from the nostrils, which means the
head is the center place that you measure from. So it sounds
like it's basically the exact same point, where do you measure from?
Okay, but we will see more about this in the גמרא. gemara.
Okay, so let's see what the גמרא gemara says. מאי טעמא דרבי
אליעזר, Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Eliezer, what's the reason of רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer that says you could have two עגלות ערופה egla arufahs for
one body if there's two towns that are equidistant? קסבר אפשר לצמצם,
Kasavar efshar l'tzamtzem, it's possible to be precise. So if two towns
are equidistant, you don't say, oh, come on, one town is clearly
closer, we're just not able to measure precisely enough. Okay, and that
would make it a ספק. safek. Now if it were a ספק
safek which town was closer and you could and we can see
that we can't measure precisely enough, then you would do what I
said a minute ago, is that you would bring one עגלה ערופה
Egla Arufa and the בתי דין batei din of each town would
like stipulate, if it's closer to mine, it's my עגלה. Egla. If
it's closer to yours, it's your עגלה ערופה. Egla Arufa. Okay, so
that would be if you said אי אפשר לצמצם. i'efshar l'tzamtzem. It's
gotta be closer. Okay, but you just can't, you know, it's like
at some level of precision it definitely would be closer to one
town, we just can't measure. No, you don't say that. You say
אפשר לצמצם. efshar l'tzamtzem. We can be precise and that there's no
meaning of going to a higher level of precision than we're able
to achieve and it really is defined as being equidistant. Okay, קסבר
אפשר לצמצם. Kasavar efshar l'tzamtzem. העיר הקרובה, ha'ir hakerova, ואפילו
קרובות.
v'afillu
krovot. Now you, okay, let's say you say fine, it is equidistant.
Now maybe there should be no עגלה ערופה, Egla Arufa, maybe there
should be an exclusion from the whole הלכה halacha because it says
העיר הקרובה ha'ir hakerova that's close, so maybe it wouldn't apply when
there are two cities. So it says no, we don't see that
the word קרובה kerova excludes the scenario of there being two cities.
So number one is we accept הלכתית halachikly that there is that
they could be defined as equidistant and we don't treat it as
a... As opposed to the other possibilities, the other two implicit possibilities
are as I said, either you bring one and you make a
תנאי, tenai, or you say it's completely exempt because since there's not
one city, it's completely exempt. He says no, you bring two. Okay.
ואין ירושלים מביאה עגלה ערופה. ve-ein Yerushalayim mevia eglah arufah. You don't
bring if Yerushalayim is the nearby city, you don't bring from Yerushalayim.
דאמר קרא de-amar kra because the פסוק pasuk says לרישתה. lerishtah. It
says that one of the cities that God is giving you for
inheritance. וקסבר ירושלים לא נתחלקה לשבטים. ve-kasvar Yerushalayim lo nitchalkah lishvatim.
Yerushalayim was not subdivided to the tribes. It was sort of an,
you know, a international city or not international, I'll get trouble for
that one,
a intertribal city, I guess, or something. Anyway, it did not was
not in the חלק chelek of any one particular tribe, so it's
not in the category of לרישתה. lerishtah. All right. נמצא ראשו במקום
אחד. nimtsa rosho b'makom echad.
Now what happens if the head is separated from the body? The
גמרא Gemara says במאי קמיפלגי. bemai kamipalgi. What's this debate about? אילימא
לעניין מדידה קמיפלגי ilima le-inyan medidah kamipalgi or where you measure from?
הא דתניא סיפא. ha detanya seifa. The end says מאיכן היו מודדין,
me-heichan hayu modedin, where were they measured from, from the belly button
or the nostrils? So מכלל דרישא לאו במדידה עסקינן. michlal d'reisha lav
b'medidah askinan. So obviously, you know, why not just mention that debate?
So the idea of head severing from the body seems to be
a different debate. Although as I pointed out, it exactly matches up,
right? רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that focuses on the head says you
measure from the nostrils, and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says you
focus on the body says you measure from the belly button. But
the fact that it's being framed as two debates seems that there's
something else going here going on here as well. So אמר רבי
יצחק, amar Rabbi Yitzchak, what else is going on here? במת מצוה
קנה מקומו
קמיפלגי. be-met mitzvah kanah mekomo kamipalgi. You're right, it's really a different
debate. It's not a debate when it's severed about where you measure
from. That's based on the end of the משנה. mishnah. It's a
debate about where you're going to bury the body. Okay, because you
bury the body where it fell in the case of a מת
מצוה. met mitzvah. All right, but what happens, right, if it didn't
fall in one place? There's two parts to the body. So הכי
קאמר hachi ka'amar לקוברו, likovro, when it comes to burying it, קנה
מקומו. kanah mekomo. It acquires its place. You bury it where it
is. והיכא דנמצא ראשו במקום אחד וגופו במקום אחר. ve-heicha denimtsa rosho
b'makom echad ve-gufo b'makom acher. Now what happens if the head and
the body are not in the same place? So מוליכין את הראש
אצל הגוף molichin et ha-rosh etsel ha-guf דברי רבי אליעזר. divrei Rabbi
Eliezer. רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, anyway, focuses on the belly button for
measuring, says you bring the head to the body and you bury
it where the body is. רבי עקיבא אומר גוף אצל הראש. Rabbi
Akiva omer guf etsel ha-rosh. You bring the body to the head
and you measure it where the head is. Okay. במאי קמיפלגי. bemai
kamipalgi. Now what's that debate about? מר סבר גופא בדוכתיה נפל רישא
דנדא
ונפל. mar savar gufa b'duchtei nafal reisha denada venafal. One holds that,
you know, presumably this guy was beheaded, so the body fell where
it was beheaded. The head flew somewhere else. So the place where
it actually was killed was where the body is, so you bring
the head to the body. That's pretty reasonable. ומר סבר רישא היכא
דנפל נפל גופא הוא דרהיט ואזל. ve-mar savar reisha heicha denafal nafal
gufa hu derahit ve-azal.
No, the head fell where it was severed from the body. גופא
הוא דרהיט ואזל. gufa hu derahit ve-azal. But the body kept on
moving, sort of like, you know, I guess a chicken that moves
around with its head cut off and imagine somebody was running away,
somebody was running after him, cut off his head, and the body
kept on going a few steps before he, yeah, the body kept
on going a few steps before it realized that there was no
head attached to it, like one of those cartoons. I don't think
that's actually possible, I don't know, but anyway. All right, makes a
lot more sense to think that the head is the thing that
flew off, not the body. Moving on. Yes.
Is the assumption, I don't remember the פסוקים, psukim, is the assumption
is nobody knows, nobody knows who this person is, right? Not like
they have relatives in that city?
Well, it doesn't say that you don't
know who the victim is, nobody knows who the murderer is. Right.
So why is this a מת מצוה met mitzvah necessarily?
Yeah, it's a good point. I think that there, the assumption of
the פרק perek hadn't occurred to me, but you're right. I mean,
the very fact that we sort of say, you know, we didn't
let him leave without accompanying him and so on, you know, it
all assumes that this is some stranger that was passing through town.
Right, right, right. I don't know why it assumes that. Right. Why
maybe it's, you know, I don't know.
It's powerful though, in other words, you have no connection, you have
responsibility.
Right, right, you're right, but I don't think the פסוקים psukim or
anything indicate that it's a stranger who's the victim, but that's certainly
the assumption here of the משניות mishnayot and of the גמרא, Gemara,
you're correct. All right. מאיכן היו מודדין, me-heichan hayu modedin, where were
they measured from, so nostrils or the belly
button. במאי קמיפלגי. bemai kamipalgi. What is this debate? מר סבר עיקר
חיותא באפי, mar savar ikar chayuta b'apei, the fundamental life is in
a person's nostrils. ומר סבר עיקר חיותא בטיבורא, ve-mar savar ikar chayuta
b'tibura, the fundamental life is in a person's belly button. Now, this
also comes up more significantly in the גמרא Gemara in יומא Yoma
about if a guy is under a pile of rubble and when
do you, how do you determine if he's still alive or not,
and do you try to measure whether he's there's still life in
his nostrils or still life in his belly button? Now, some people
want to make this a debate about whether life is measured by
breathing or by circulation, although what belly button has to do with
circulation. There's some גירסא girsa about heart, but belly button certainly is
the, you know, almost definitely is the right גירסא, girsa,
and it really seems... that both of those, well we'll see in
a minute of the גמרא, Gemara, but both of those could be
related to breathing,
because the belly button is like the diaphragm and the rising and
the falling or whatever, so they could both very much be related
to breathing and we'll see in a minute that the גמרא Gemara
does tie it in very much to the idea of breath. So,
so let's take a look. Although this isn't saying this as a
way of determining whether a person is alive or not, but like
where we locate the, we sort of say the locus of life.
לימא כי הני תנאי, Lima ke-hanni Tannai, let's say it's like this
debate of תנאי. Tannai. מהיכן הולד נוצר, Meheichan ha-valad notzar, where is
the child, from where does the child sort of develop, you know
how is he created, developed in the uterus? מראשו, Me-rosho, from the
head. Like the head is created first and then the rest of
the body comes after. וכן הוא אומר ממעי אמי אתה גוזי, Ve-chein
hu omer mi-mei immi attah gozi, from my mother's womb you fashioned
me. And גוזי, Gozi, רש"י Rashi says is, ואומר גזי נזרך והשליכי,
Ve-omer gozi nizreich ve-hashlichi, cut off your whatever,
your locks and throw them. So רש"י Rashi says, how does רש"י
Rashi say that גוזי Gozi means this?
אתה מראשי יצרת, Attah me-roshi yatzarta, ראשי תחילה, Roshi techillah, גוזי Gozi
לשון רישא, Lashon reisha,
גזי נזרכי, Gozi nizreichi, שער ראשך. Se'ar roshecha. So the גזי נזרך
והשליכי, Gozi nizreich ve-hashlichi, רש"י Rashi says means, גוז Goz means the
head, and נזרך Nizreich like the נזיר's, Nazir the hair of the
head. Okay, so somehow גוזי Gozi means the head.
Where were we? אבא שאול אומר מטיבורו, Abba Shaul omer mi-tibburo, no,
the infant is created from the, fetus develops from the belly button.
ומשגר שרשו אילך ואילך, U-meshageir shoresho eilach va-eilach, because the belly button
is like in the middle. So it starts in the middle and
then it, you know, grows out in all directions. וכן הוא אומר
ממעי אמי אתה גוזי. Ve-chein hu omer mi-mei immi attah gozi. ואפילו
תימא אבא שאול. Ve-afilu teima Abba Shaul. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, it could even be even be אבא שאול
Abba Shaul who says that the, that from the belly button, he
could agree that here that it would go by the nostrils. עד
כאן לא קאמר אבא שאול אלא לעניין יצירה, Ad kan la ka'amar
Abba Shaul ella le-inyan yetzirah, when it comes to the developing of
the infant. דכי מיצר ולד ממציעיתיה מיצר, De-chi miytzar valad mi-metzi'ateih miytzar,
when it develops it develops from the middle. אבל לעניין חיותא, Aval
le-inyan chiyuta, when it comes to where is the life force, דכולי
עלמא באפיה הוא. De-chulei alma be-appeih hu. Now everyone, because it's not
what do you call it, ר' אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer in the משנה,
Mishnah, but everyone in the sense of אבא שאול Abba Shaul and
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma here, would all agree that it's in
the nostrils.
שדכתיב, She-dichtiv, as it says, כל אשר נשמת רוח חיים באפיו, Kol
asher nishmat ruach chayyim be-appav, that the spirit of life is in
their nostrils. So the גמרא Gemara very much here and in יומא
Yoma and elsewhere, you know, constantly basically comes down on the side
that whether it's a question of where do you measure from the,
from the what do you call it, for the עגלה ערופה, Eglah
Arufah, or how do you determine life, it's determined by breath in
the nostrils. And again, even טיבורו Tibburo really could be not denying
the idea of breath but just measuring it from a different place
or conceptualizing its locus in a different place, which is very significant,
you know, in terms of contemporary discussions around halakhic definition of death
and so on. Because, well whatever, I won't get on my soapbox
about that. Moving on. Okay. Yes.
הסוגיא ביומא היא הסוגיא דפיקוח נפש Ha-sugya be-Yoma hi ha-sugya de-pikuach nefesh
sugya about on שבת Shabbos and you move the rocks.
Yeah, exactly. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר ממקום שנעשה חלל מצוארו, Rabbi
Elazar ben Yaakov omer mi-makom she-na'asah challal mi-tzavvaro, and he says not
from the nostrils or the belly button, but from the neck. מאי
טעמא דרבי אלעזר בן יעקב? Mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov? כדכתיב,
Ki-dechtiv, לתת אותך על צוארי חללי רשעים, Latet otcha al tzavverei challalei
resha'im, to put you over the necks of the corpses of the
wicked. So the context, the image of the idea of a corpse,
of certainly a corpse by a sword, we discussed before about whether
חלל Challal meant by a sword, is an idea of a severed
head. Okay, so therefore the definition of חלל Challal would be by
the neck. Fine. So that's how, now we've measured. So it's the
בית דין Beit Din in ירושלים Yerushalayim that comes out and measures,
and then it's the local בית דין Beit Din of the nearby
city that comes out and does the ritual now that we've identified
the city. נפטרו זקני ירושלים והלכו להם, Niftaru ziknei Yerushalayim ve-halchu lahem,
the elders of ירושלים Yerushalayim left. וזקני אותה העיר מביאין עגלה בקר.
Ve-ziknei otah ha-ir mevi'in eglah bakar. Now you do the ritual. So
the elders of that city, of the nearby city, bring a calf
of, you know, from a of a cow. אשר לא משכה בעול,
Asher lo mashcha be-ol, that did not draw a yoke.
ואין המום פוסל בה, Ve-ein ha-mum posel bah, but a blemish is
not a problem. Having walked with a yoke is a problem but
not a blemish.
ומורידין אותה לנחל איתן, U-moridin otah le-nachal eitan, and they bring it
down to the wadi of איתן. Eitan. What does איתן Eitan mean?
איתן כמשמעו קשה, Eitan ke-mashma'o kasheh, it's hard, hard rock. אף על
פי שאינו איתן כשר, Af al pi she-eino eitan kasher, but that's
only a לכתחילה. lechatchilah. Even if it was not a hard valley,
wadi, it would still be kosher. ועורפין אותה בקופיץ מאחוריה, Ve-orfin otah
be-kofitz me-achoreha, and they cut off its head with a hatchet from
behind its neck. ומקומו אסור מלזרוע, U-mekomo assur milizro'a, and the place
where they do this, you are not allowed to plant. I mean,
if it's a good hard rock to begin with, that won't be
that much of a problem. ומלעבוד, U-milla'avod, and you can't do other
types of work on
the, you know, in the on the ground. לעולם, Le-olam, forever. Right.
But ומותר לסרוק שם פשתן ולנקר שם אבנים. U-muttar lisrok sham pishtan
u-lenaker sham avanim. Now you can do things on that place as
long as you're not using the ground, like planting and harvesting the
ground. So you can use it as a place to comb flax.
To clean out stones, right? It's not like you can't stand and
sit on the place, but you can't like use the ground. In
the soil. In the soil. Right, soil maybe is the better word
there. זקני אותה עיר רוחצים את ידיהם במים במקום עריפה arifa *ziknei
oso ir rochtzin es yedeihem bemayim bemakom arifah*. Now the elders wash
their hands with water, this is in the פסוקים psukim *pesukim*, where
the breaking of the neck took place, במקום עריפה *bemakom arifah* of
the עגלה eglah *eglah*, and they say ידינו לא שפכו את הדם
הזה *yadeinu lo shafchu es hadam hazeh* like they're washing, it's actually
funny, because on the one hand it's about taking responsibility. On the
other hand, the ritual itself is almost visually it feels a little
bit like denying responsibility. I wash my hands from you. They're washing
their hands and they're saying we have no culpability. Our hands didn't
spill this blood. Right, it's very funny, it almost feels a little
bit like denying responsibility. But maybe there's an idea that visually, conceptually,
there is some blood on their hands that has to be cleansed
through the washing. If you think again, I'm maybe being influenced by
the idiom that I wash my hands of this, which means I'm
moving on, walking away from this. This isn't my problem. But maybe
it's both ideas. Your hands were dirty and you have to do
something to free yourself from it. Okay. So our hands have not
spilled this blood, ועינינו לא ראו *ve'eineinu lo ra'u*, our eyes did
not see what happened. וכי על דעתנו עלתה שזקני בית דין beis
din שופכי דמים הם *vechi al da'ateinu altah sheziknei beisin shofchei damim
hem*? Why, would it occur to us that they were the murderers?
They have to say we did not spill this blood? אלא שלא
בא לידינו ופטרנוהו בלא מזונות ולא פטרנוהו בלא ראינוהו והנחנוהו *ela shelo
ba leyadeinu upaternuhu belo mezonot velo paternuhu belo re'inuhu vehinanuchu*. He did
not come to us and we did
not just
abandon him and we didn't see him and leave him alone. If
he, we were not aware, meaning it's not that we did not
actively murder him, but we don't have any culpability here. It's not
that this was somebody that we knew about and that we should've
taken better care of that we didn't take care of. Which actually
would interestingly mean that it doesn't address this issue, but let's say
a guy walked through town and he was asking for a place
to stay and nobody was helping out or I don't know if
the בית דין *beit din* knew about it and they weren't getting
involved, then they wouldn't be able to do this
ritual, right? The ritual is actually one they're saying of claiming not
just that they did not murder, but they did not have any
culpability, they were not aware that this person needed help. Okay, והכהנים
אומרים *vehakohanim omrim* and the כהנים *kohanim* say כפר לעמך ישראל אשר
Asher פדית ה' *kaper le'amcha yisrael asher padita hashem* atone for your
people that you have redeemed God, ואל תתן דם נקי בקרב עמך
ישראל *ve'al titein dam naki bekerev amcha yisrael* do not give the
guilt of this innocent blood on your people. לא היו צריכים לומר
ונכפר להם הדם *lo hayu tzrichim lomar venichapeir lahem hadam* now the
end of the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* there in the תורה *torah* says
ונכפר להם הדם *venichapeir lahem hadam*, the blood shall be atoned for
them, the
משנה Mishnah *mishnah* is saying that's not part of the quotes, that's
not what the כהנים *kohanim* are saying. That's what the תורה *torah*
is saying. אלא רוח הקודש מבשרתם *ela ruach hakodesh mevasertam*, the divine
spirit, meaning the תורה *torah* is telling them if you do this
ritual, אימתי שתעשו ככה *eimatai sheta'asu kachah*, if you go through with
this ritual, הדם יתכפר להם *hadam yitkaper lahem* then you'll be atoned
for the blood. Okay, but that's not in the quote marks of
the כהנים *kohanim*. Let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *gemara*.
Yeah, when usually you שחיטה *shechitah* from below, right?
Yeah, so this is of the opposite.
What do you think that's about?
Well, it's about the violence of the act, as opposed to שחיטה
*shechitah* is like the controlled releasing of blood and this is like
the violence.
And it's not a קרבן korban. *korban*, you don't want to confuse
it with a קרבן korban *korban* either. I mean, that's also funny,
there's a sense of spilling blood to atone. A קרבן korban. *korban*
is a blood that atones. I mean, there's also פרה אדומה Parah
Adumah, *parah adumah* which is actually exactly what the גמרא Gemara *gemara*'s
going to say, which is like a pseudo-קרבן korban, *korban* that gets
done out of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *beit hamikdash*, but that
gets שחיטה *shechted* and the blood gets sprinkled, right? So that has
more of a קרבן korban. *korban* dimension, this is something else. Like
maybe also if one wants to think about I don't know, like
the שעיר לעזאזל *sa'ir la'azazel*. Okay, although here that's just sent off.
This is actually out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *beit hamikdash*,
it's very much a non-קרבן korban, *korban*, like as you point out,
it's not the שחיטה *shechitah* from the front, it's the whatever, it's
from the back, it's a, but on the other hand, there's something
about the blood and the atoning in this way. So but it's
not fit for in terms of the normal ritualized way of the
קרבן korban. *korban* way of doing it. Yeah.
Is it, would you have expected it to say הדם מכפר להם
*hadam mechaper lahem*?
No, that's a good point and that gets to David's point. We're
not talking about the blood of the עגלה eglah *eglo*. We're talking
about the blood that was spilled. Oh, so that's a very good
point. Right, it's ונכפר להם *venichapeir lahem* for the, אל תתן דם
נקי *al titein dam naki*, innocent blood was spilled and it needs
atoning for it, because it says כי לארץ לא יכופר לדם אשר
Asher שפך בה bah כי אם בדם שופכו *ki la'aretz lo yechupar
ladam asher shupach bah ki im bedam shofcho*. The only way the
innocent blood is atoned for is by the execution of the murderer.
This doesn't have the דם שופכו *dam shofcho*. So what you have
is you have an execution of an innocent עגלה eglah *eglah* which
to some degree is a substitute for executing the murderer, and that
atones for the innocent blood,
but it's the, it's not the blood of... The עגלה eglah that's
atoning, it's the innocent blood that's being atoned for. Okay, but it
is, it's very compelling and interesting that it's not exactly, it's not
a
קרבן. korban? I think that's an interesting way of thinking about it.
Is it more of a קרבן korban or is it more of
a substitute execution of the murderer if you would have had the
murderer, right? And there's actually some and there is an execution in
the בית המקדש that is
by the sword, which
according to some is actually a type of a
קופיץ kopitz execution. There's a question exactly how it would be, but
it could very well have been a form of execution that
it uses a קופיץ. kopitz.
Exactly, exactly. So seeing this as a type of a substitute execution
of had the would-be murderer, or of the murderer who we don't
know who he is. Okay. So, this is actually... okay, sorry. So
ואמרו פוסל בעגלה מעגלה קל וחומר. V’amru posel b’eglah m’eglah kal v’chomer.
So the משנה says that a מום mum is not a פסול,
posul, which again points to the fact that it's not a קרבן.
korban. So it says why don't we say it's a פסול posul
based on a קל וחומר kal v’chomer from פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah,
which is also not exactly a קרבן, korban, although a lot closer
to a קרבן. korban ומה פרה שאין השנים פוסל בה מום פוסל
בה, U’mah parah she’ein ha’shanim posel bah mum posel bah, by a
פרה parah the age doesn't matter and nevertheless a מום mum matters,
עגלה שהשנים פוסל בה, eglah she’shanim posel bah, an עגלה eglah that
has to be one year old,
it
says because an עגלה eglah means a one-year-old, that's what we assume,
so
the years can invalidate, אינו דין שמום פוסל בה, eino din she’mum
posel bah, certainly a מום mum should invalidate, should have more requirements.
So the גמרא Gemara says no. שאני התם דאמר קרא, Shani hatam
d’amar k’ra, it says by the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah אשר אין
בה מום. asher ein bah mum. There's no מום mum in it.
בה מום פוסל, bah mum posel, by a פרה אדומה Parah Adumah,
a מום mum is a problem, ואין מום פוסל בעגלה, v’ein mum
posel b’eglah, but it's not a problem by the calf. So the
גמרא Gemara says okay, אלא מעתה לא ישאר עבודות פוסל בה. ella
me’atah lo yeshar avodos posel bah. So if that's true, that the
בה bah is a limiting word and we don't take one idea
that we have by עגלה eglah and apply it to the פרה
parah or vice versa, so then we should say that other acts
of עבודה avodah of labor do not invalidate a פרה אדומה, Parah
Adumah because by the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah it doesn't say... by
the עגלה eglah. it says אשר לא עבד בה, asher lo uvad
bah, that was not worked. By the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah it
says פרה אדומה תמימה אשר אין בה מום אשר לא עלה עליה
עול. Parah Adumah temimah asher ein bah mum asher lo alah aleha
ol. It did not have a yoke. But let's say you used
it to do an עבודה avodah that was not a yoke. Okay?
So there's nothing in the פסוקים psukim. by פרה אדומה Parah Adumah.
that says it's פסול. posul. We learn it out from the עגלה
ערופה, Eglah Arufah, because the עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah says אשר לא
עבד בה. asher lo uvad bah. But by עגלה eglah. it says
אשר לא עבד בה. asher lo uvad bah. So if we're not
going to apply the idea of a מום mum from פרה parah
to עגלה eglah because it says
אשר אין בה
מום,
asher
ein bah
mum, then we shouldn't apply...
right? By the פרה parah it says
פרה אדומה תמימה
אשר אין בה מום
אשר לא עלה עליה עול.
Parah Adumah temimah asher ein bah mum asher
lo alah aleha
ol. And by the עגלה eglah it
says עגלת בקר
אשר לא עבד בה אשר
לא משכה
בעול.
eglat bakar asher lo uvad bah asher lo
mashcha b’ol. Okay, so we said how do we know מום mum
doesn't apply? Because it says בה מום. bah mum. So by פרה
parah it's only a מום, mum, not by עגלה. eglah. Okay, but
it doesn't say here anything about עבודה. avodah. It says מום mum
and עול, ol, it doesn't say עבודה. avodah. Here it says אשר
לא עבד בה. asher lo uvad bah. So if we're going to
say בה bah doesn't allow, you can't learn out, so this should
say עבודה avodah only פוסל posel by עגלה. eglah? It doesn't פוסל
posel by the פרה, parah, right? The בה bah should be the
same limiting idea. But we're going to see that that's not true.
So let's take a look. It says אלא
מעתה לא ישאר עבודות פוסל בה, ella me’atah lo yeshar avodos posel
bah, other עבודות avodos other than an עול ol should not invalidate
by a פרה אדומה. Parah Aduma. ולמה תני ולמה אמר רבי יהודה
אמר רב, Velama tani velama amar Rabbi Yehuda amar Rav, why does
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda say in the name of רב, Rav, הניח
לה עדה של שקים, hiniach lah oda shel sakim, if you put
a bundle of sacks on the פרה, parah, פסולה, psulah, it's invalid,
even though that's not an עול. ol. An עול ol presumably has
to be literally like a yoke. Okay? ובעגלה עד שתמשוך, U’ve’eglah ad
she’timshoch, and by an עגלה eglah. it's not enough that the עול
ol that this thing was put on it, it has to actually
carry
this burden and what you're putting on it. So we'll bracket for
now the reason why עגלה Egla is different than פרה. parah. Nevertheless,
it doesn't say anything other than עול ol by פרה. parah. So
if this is true by פרה, parah, it must be we learn
it out from עבד בה uvad bah by עגלה. Egla, But why
doesn't the word בה ba say that no, עבודה avodah is only
a problem by עגלה? Egla. So the גמרא Gemara says שאני פרה
דילפינן עול עול מעגלה. Shani parah d’yalfinnan ol ol me’eglah. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, we learn it out עול עול ol ol
from עגלה. Egla. are able to learn out עבודה avoda because it
says עול עול ol ol and that allows us to learn out
עבודה. avoda. So of course the point is so then we're going
to say עבודה avoda also applies. Of course if you're going to
use this to learn out עבודה, avoda, you could use this to
learn out מום, mum, right? Right? If you're going to apply עבודה
avoda from עגלה Egla to פרה, Parah, you should use the עול
עול ol ol to apply מום mum from פרה Parah to עגלה,
Egla which is what the גמרא Gemara is going to say.
Why? עול ol is שייך shayach to עבודה, avoda, it's not שייך
shayach to...
well, doesn't matter though, they're different kind of... I mean, okay, somewhat
conceptually related, but still it's different parts of the פסוק. pasuk Okay,
once you have a גזירה שוה, gzera shava, if you can learn
this phrase, you can learn that phrase. All right, so the גמרא
Gemara
says עגלה נמי תיתי עול עול מפרה Egla nami teisi ol ol
mi'Parah to learn out the idea of מום. mum. המיעט רחמנא בה.
ha'mi'eit rachmana ba. No, it says אשר אין בה מום. asher ein
ba mum. So בעגלה נמי כתיב בה אשר לא עובד בה. b'Egla
nami ksiv ba asher lo ubad ba. So again, we're back to
square one. בה ba, should limit it to עגלה. Egla
So the גמרא Gemara says ההיא מיבעי ליה למיעוטי קדשים דלא פסלה
בהו עבודה. hahi mibai lei l'mi'utei kodshim d'lo pasla behu avoda. No,
no, no. That בה, ba you're right, this is really the answer.
בה מום ba mum here says מום mum is only a problem
by פרה. Parah. Now, you don't have to exclude anything else from
a problem by מום, mum, because you know what else you know
what definitely is a problem with a מום? mum? What things cannot
have a מום? mum? What things can't have
a מום?
mum? The sacrifices.
קרבנות. korbanos. So you have the whole world here of קרבנות. korbanos.
Okay, we know that קרבנות, korbanos, מום mum is a problem. So
if בה ba is telling me מום mum is only a problem
by פרה, Parah, it's not excluding קרבנות, korbanos, it's saying it's not
a problem by עגלה ערופה, Egla Arufa, right? Okay, but by here,
it says אשר לא עובד בה, asher lo ubad ba, it's telling
me עבודה avoda is only a problem here and not elsewhere. That's
what the בה ba is telling me. What it's actually doing is
it's not excluding פרה, Parah, you know what it's excluding? It's excluding
קרבנות. korbanos. קרבנות, korbanos, surprisingly, עבודה avoda does not invalidate. Okay, so
בה ba here says מום mum is not a problem by עגלה.
Egla בה ba here does not say it's not a problem by
פרה, Parah, בה ba here says עבודה avoda is not a problem
by קרבנות, korbanos, which is quite shocking, right? You would think the
you would think that
קרבנות korbanos are always weightier. Okay, but that shows you that we're
more interested in seeing these in a similar category than קרבנות, korbanos,
because in the end, these are being done outside the בית המקדש.
So it's true there's a מום mum idea here, and we're not
going to extend the מום mum idea. Maybe דווקא davka a reason
not to extend the מום mum idea to עגלה Egla, is exactly
what I said, extending the מום mum idea to עגלה Egla. makes
it more like a קרבן, korban. and it's not like a קרבן.
korban You don't sprinkle the blood, you don't slaughter it in the
ritual way. So we're not going to extend that. But this idea
of עבודה, avoda, that's limited to עגלה eglah and פרה, Parah, it
doesn't apply to קרבנות. korbanos. Okay, so the בה ba here does
not exclude פרה. Parah. The בה ba, here only excludes קרבנות. korbanos.
עבודה avoda is not a problem by קרבנות. korbanos.
The fact that you can work
an animal that then be a קרבן? korban Yeah, it's a powerful
idea conceptually.
That animal that's been plowing your field and that really was connected
to...
it's a nice idea, right.
That then you could be מקדיש makdish it as long as it
meets other criteria and
and create a bridge to the domain of the sacred.
It's a very nice idea.
יישר כח. yasher koach. Okay, so it says ומה עגלה שאין מום
פוסל בה... u'ma Egla she'ein mum posel ba... Okay, it says מיבעי
ליה למיעוטי קדשים דלא פסלה בהו עבודה. mibai lei l'mi'utei kodshim d'lo
pasla behu avoda. עבודה avoda is not a problem by
קרבנות. korbanos. סלקא דעתך אמינא ליתי בקל וחומר מעגלה. salka dach'tach amina
leisi b'kal v'chomer me'Egla. Learn a קל וחומר kal v'chomer from עגלה
ערופה. Egla Arufa. מה עגלה שאין מום פוסל בה עבודה פוסלת בה,
ma Egla she'ein mum posel ba avoda poseles ba, קדשים שמום פוסל
בהן אינו דין שעבודה פוסלת בהן? kodshim she'mum posel bahen eino din
she'avoda poseles bahen? Very reasonable assumption, I certainly would have assumed that.
So therefore it tells me בה, ba that עבודה avoda is not
a problem by קדשים, kodshim, but it is a problem by פרה
אדומה. parah adumah. No, איכא למפרך, ika l'mifrach, I could have challenged.
מה לעגלה שכן שנים פוסלות בה, ma l'Egla she'ken shanim poslos ba,
I wouldn't have made that קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. I would have
said an עגלה eglah. has to be only one year, it's age
invalidated. So therefore I can't apply the idea of עבודה avoda to
קרבנות korbanos because קרבנות korbanos age doesn't matter. So the גמרא Gemara
says who says it doesn't matter by קרבנות? korbanos? אטו קדשים מי
ליכא דפסיל בהו שנים? atu kodshim mi lika d'pasila behu shanim? Are
you telling me there are no קרבנות korbanos that years matter? Like
there is. Like קרבן פסח Korban Pesach has to be a year
old, there's some קרבנות korbanos that years matter.
So כי איצטריך קרא להנך קדשים דפסיל בהו שנים. ki itzterich kra
l'hanach kodshim d'pasila behu shanim. I need a פסוק pasuk: that those
קרבנות korbanos that years do matter, I have a total קל וחומר.
kal v'chomer. עגלה, eglah מום mum doesn't matter
and עבודה avoda does, קרבנות korbanos where מום mum does matter how
much more so should עבודה avoda matter? And in both of those
cases, there are cases of קרבנות korbanos that also years matter, just
like by עגלה. eglah. So it's the same קל וחומר. kal v'chomer.
So that's why I needed בה ba to tell me that עבודה
avoda does not matter by קרבנות. korbanos.
Okay, so that's what we have. עבודה avoda doesn't matter.
So מום mum tells me מום mum is only by פרה. Parah.
בה ba here does not limit פרה. Parah. פרה עבודה's Parah avoda
also an issue. It says by קרבנות korbanos עבודה avoda does not
matter.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
וקדשים דלא פסלה בהו עבודה מהכא נפקא?
v'kodshim d'lo
pasla behu avoda me'hacha nafka?
Is that where we learned that קדשים kodshim עבודה avoda doesn't invalidate
from the בה bah by... עגלה ערופה? eglah arufa? מהתם נפקא. mehasom
nafka. We learn it from a different פסוק: pasuk עור או שבור
או חרוץ או יבלת או גרב או ילפת לא תקריבו אלה לה׳.
iver o shavur o charutz o yavelet o garav o yalefet lo
takrivu eleh la-Hashem. So that's by different types of blemishes. אלה אתה
מקריב, eleh atah makriv, you can't bring those animals with blemishes. לא
תקריבו אלה לה׳, lo takrivu eleh la-Hashem, אבל אתה מקריב קדשים שנעבדה
בהן עבודה, aval atah makriv kadshim she-ne'evdah bahen avodah, but if it's
just that they used it to do work, that you could bring.
So we learn it out from the אלה. eleh. We don't need
the בה by עגלה ערופה eglah arufa to tell you עבודה avodah
isn't a problem. But it says איצטריך. itstreech. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka
daitach amina, I need the extra פסוק pasuk by the עגלה ערופה.
eglah arufa. I would have thought הני מילי היכא דעבד בהן עבודת
היתר. hani milei hicha d'avad bahen avodat heter. When is it not
invalidated for קרבן if you used it for normal permissible labor like
to plow your land? אבל עבודת איסור, aval avodat issur, if you
use it for an איסור, issur, like let's say you yoked it
with כלאים kilayim let's say, you know, or you had to plow
a field of כלאים kilayim or something, אימא ליצרו, eima litzro, let's
say it becomes forbidden like that type of מצוה הבאה בעבירה mitzvah
ha-ba'ah b'aveirah or to blemish on it, a, you know, like a
metaphysical blemish. צריכה, tzricha, no you need it. Again, a very powerful
idea. You can do עבודה, avodah, you can do עבודה avodah on
it, you know, even, even באיסור b'issur and it does, and the
animal can still be used to be brought as a קרבן. Okay,
so that's why you need the two פסוקים. psukim והא נמי מהכא
נפקא? v'ha nami mehacha nafka? One minute, there's a, we have yet
another פסוק pasuk that we learn that עבודה avodah isn't a problem
that can teach us that. ומיד בן נכר לא תקריבו את לחם
אלוהיכם מכל אלה, u-mi-yad ben nechar lo takrivu et lechem eloheichem mi-kol
eleh, do not bring, do not accept a sacrifice from a foreigner,
from a non-Jew from these, from animals with blemishes. אלה אתה מקריב,
eleh atah makriv, you can't bring these animals,
אבל אתה מקריב קדשים שנעבדה בהן עבודה. aval atah makriv kadshim she-ne'evdah
bahen avodah. So we have now three פסוקים psukim to tell you
an עבודה's avodah not a problem by קרבנות. korbanot. Why do you
need all three? איצטריך. itstreech. No, you need all three. סלקא דעתך
אמינא salka daitach amina הני מילי היכא דעבד בהן כשהן חולין. hani
milei hicha d'avad bahen keshein chullin. Even two פסוקים Pesukim, would have
told me whether it's עבודת היתר, avodat heter, whether it's עבודת איסור,
avodat issur, that's not a problem as long as you used it
when it had not yet been sanctified. אבל עבד בהן כשהן קדשים,
aval avad bahen keshein kadshim, but if you actually worked the animal
when it was a קרבן, that I would say would really compromise
its קדושה, kedusha, you know, you had really violated its קדושה kedusha
status, אימא ליצרו, eima litzro, let it become forbidden. צריכה, tzricha, it
tells you it doesn't. So that's quite a big surprise. Right? Who
knew that עבודה avodah did not invalidate by קדשים kadshim even if
you did the עבודה avodah when they were קדשים? kadshim? That does
not invalidate.
Why isn't it a מעילה? me'ilah?
I don't get that. You might be a מעילה, me'ilah, but the
קרבן is still כשר. kasher. You didn't change the status of the
קרבן. Okay, its קדושה kedusha wasn't compromised.
You don't have to substitute it for another?
No. Yeah, pretty surprising, right? So מום mum is a problem by
פרה, parah, עבודה avodah is a problem by both of them. קרבנות
korbanot you've got so by פרה parah מום mum and עבודה avodah
is a problem. By עגלה eglah, it's just, it's just עבודה avodah
because it doesn't really have a קרבן status, and by קרבן it's
just מום. mum. So it's actually interesting, right? These are like mirror
images of one another. This is just מום mum is a problem,
not עבודה. avodah. This is just עבודה avodah and not מום. mum.
And this has both problems, פרה אדומה. parah adumah, Okay. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like
this:
גופא. gufa. Let's go back to the original statement. אמר רב יהודה
אמר
רב: amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav: המניח חבילה של שקין hamaniach chavilah
shel sakin on the פרה אדומה, Para Aduma. פסולה. psulah. It's invalid.
Even if it just, like,
carried a burden, even though it wasn't an עול, ol, a yoke.
ובעגלה עד שתמשוך. u-v'eglah ad she-timshoch. It has to draw because it
says אשר לא משכה בעול. asher lo mashcha b'ol. All right, although
this is not exactly an עול ol technically. מיתיבי. meitivi. Now the
גמרא Gemara says last one on this: עול. אין לי אלא עול.
שאר עבודות מנין? Ol Ein Li Ela Ol She-ar Avodot Minayin? Okay,
so I only know אשר לא עלה עליה עול asher lo ala
aleha ol by a פרה. parah. How do I know other things
are a problem that are not an עול ol. by a פרה?
parah? אמרת קל וחומר. amarta kal vachomer. ומה עגלה שאין מום פוסל
בה שאר עבודות פוסלות בה. u-mah eglah she-ein mum posel bah shear
avodot poslot bah. This is sort of what we were saying before,
right? That we're going to learn פרה parah from עגלה. eglah? עגלה
eglah? does not have a blemish as a problem, עבודה's avodah a
problem, פרה שמום פוסל בה, parah she-mum posel bah, פרה parah that
has a blemish as a problem, אינו דין שאר עבודות פוסלות בה?
eino din shear avodot poslot bah? Okay, certainly עבודה avodah should
be a problem. So basically we learn עבודה, avodah, like we've been
saying, for to פרה parah from עגלה. eglah, But here's the problem.
If we're learning the idea of עבודה avodah to פרה parah from
it's that from
עגלה, eglah how could it be a different parameters than עגלה? eglah
How could it be more strict than עגלה? eglah Okay. ואי משום
דאיכא למימר. v'i mishum d'ika l'meimar. Anyway,
so what is the קל וחומר? kal vachomer? If you don't like
the קל וחומר, kal vachomer, נאמר כאן עול
ונאמר להלן
עול. ne'emar kan ol v'ne'emar lehalan ol. It's a גזירה שוה. gezeirah
shavah. מה להלן שאר עבודות פוסלות
בה,
mah lehalan
shear avodot poslot bah,
the same way עבודה avodah passuls by עגלה, Egla אף כאן שאר
עבודות פוסלות בה af kan shear avodot poslot bah passuls by פרה.
parah. מאי אי משום דאיכא למימר? mai i mishum d'ika l'meimar?
Why did you have to go to a קל וחומר? kal vachomer?
גזירה שוה? gezeirah shavah? What was wrong with the קל וחומר? kal
vachomer?
דכי תימא איכא למיפרך, d'chi teima ika l'mifrach, you can ask, מה
לעגלה שכן שנים פוסלות בה? mah l'eglah she-kein shanim poslot bah? First
of all, it's not necessarily a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. There's ways
in which עגלה Egla is stricter than פרה. parah. עגלה Egla. has
to be a year old. פרה parah does not have years of,
as an, as an
invalidate. So just because something is a problem by עגלה Egla, doesn't
mean it's a problem by פרה. parah. אי נמי או קדשים יוכיחו.
i nami o kadshim yochichu. There's another way that... קדשים kodashim have
מום mum and not עבודה, avoda, there would be so there's not
a קל וחומר kal vachomer to teach you עבודה avoda by פרה.
Para. We know מום, mum, it's stricter than עגלה Egla because it
has מום mum and עגלה Egla does not have a מום mum
problem, but nevertheless, it might not have an עבודה avoda problem. So
that's the גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah of עול עול. ol ol. עול
עול ol ol tells us alright, you couldn't have learned it out
logically, but עול עול ol ol is telling you there is an
עבודה avoda problem by פרה. Para.
Okay, in the hierarchy of hermeneutics, which is generally stronger, the סברא
sevara of קל וחומר kal vachomer or גזירה שוה? gezeirah shavah?
Well, a סברא sevara of קל וחומר kal vachomer is more attractive
because it's logical, but it's also because of that reason it's more
able to be challenged. גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah is you know is
more arbitrary, so it's also less able to be challenged. Okay, I
mean I mean also all things being equal, would there be a
preference for doing one rather than the other? I don't know. It
sounds like not. It sounds like we'd rather do a קל וחומר
kal vachomer if קל וחומר kal vachomer works.
Okay.
You can't make up a new גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah too, right?
Correct, correct. You either have a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah and that's
it.
Yeah, it seems to be. Correct. Okay. Okay, so אלא מה עול
מה להלן עבודה אף כאן עבודה. al ma ol ma lehalan avoda
af kan avoda. ומי מכדי עכשיו umi michdi achshav the גמרא אומרת,
hagemara omeret, fine, so we learn עבודה avoda from עגלה. Egla. But
if we're learning it from עגלה, Egla it should be the same
definition. So if עגלה Egla is a problem as still it the...
if
עגלה Egla, is
not a problem until it carries the the burden, so פרה Para
should also be the same because the whole source is עגלה. Egla.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara says: ומי מכדי, umi michdi, one
minute, you have to learn out from where you're coming from. מה
להלן עד שתמשוך אף כאן עד שתמשוך. ma lehalan ad she-timshoch af
kan ad she-timshoch. If the source is עגלה Egla and עגלה Egla,
is not a problem until it actually walks with the burden, the
same should be by the פרה. Para. So the גמרא Gemara says
you know what, you're right. If you learned it from עגלה, Egla.
it would be the same definition. This statement of רב יהודה אמר
רב Rav Yehuda amar Rav is going from a different source by
פרה Para that doesn't learn it from עגלה. Egla תנאי היא, tanai
hi, it's a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. דאיכא דמייתי לה מעגלה, de-ika
de-maiti leh me-Egla, there are those that learn עבודה avoda for פרה
Para from עגלה Egla and then it would be the same definition.
איכא דמייתי לה מגופה דפרה, ika de-maiti leh mi-gufeh de-Para, but some
learn it intrinsically from פרה Para: אדומה. דתניא, de-tanya, we taught in
a ברייתא: braita: או, o, אין לי אלא עול. ein li ela
ol. It says by פרה: Para אשר לא עלה עליה עול. asher
lo ala aleha ol. Okay, I only know if a yoke was
put on it. שאר עבודה מנין, shear avoda minayin, how do I
know if something other than a yoke was put on it? תלמוד
לומר: talmud lomar: אשר לא עלה עליה. asher lo ala aleha. Okay,
it didn't again, with these they want to use funny דרשות, drashot,
but since it left the word עול ol till the end, it
could have said אשר לא עלה עול עליה. asher lo ala ol
aleha. But it says עליה עול, aleha ol, which means you stop
the פסוק before you get to the word עול. ol If anything
wasn't put on it, so we're not going to limit it to
yoke. So the idea of doing something else is not based on
a concept of עבודה, avoda, it's also a conceptual difference. Here's a
concept of עבודה. avoda. Here what we're doing is it's not a
concept of עבודה. avoda. It's just we're saying nothing is put on
it. We're just saying that the word yoke is less specific. So
if you put anything on it, that's why when you put the
package of sacks on it, even if it didn't walk with it,
it didn't do an עבודה, avoda, the concept of the פרה Para,
we're saying this is not about עבודה. avoda. It's about anything being
put on it. Okay, so אם כן מה תלמוד לומר עול? im
ken ma talmud lomar ol? או? o? אשר לא עלה עליה עול
asher lo ala aleha ol מכל מקום mikol makom or it could
just be מכל מקום. mikol makom. אם כן מה תלמוד לומר עול?
im ken ma talmud lomar ol? So if it's just about anything
being put on it by פרה, Para what's the meaning of the
word עול? ol. עול פוסל בין בשעת עבודה בין שלא בשעת עבודה.
ol posel bein be-sha'at avoda bein she-lo be-sha'at avoda. Because if you
put a yoke on it, it invalidates it whether you're using it
to do work or not using it to do work.
So עול ol? does not inform the definition of עבודה. avoda.
Right, well, we're actually bracketing עבודה avoda according to this approach, it's
not conceptually about עבודה avoda by פרה Para. you know that much
at all. It's really just about עלה עליה. ala aleha. That's right.
Just about the עול ol or any burden.
שאר עבודות אין פוסלות אלא בשעת עבודה. shear avodot ein poslot ela
be-sha'at avoda. Okay, other things, now what does it mean בשעת עבודה?
be-sha'at avoda? When you put a when you put a thing of
sacks on it, what בשעת עבודה be-sha'at avoda is it?
So רש"י... Rashi...
no, but it doesn't. The whole point is even if it didn't
take a step by by other things. Why did it... right it
says as soon as you put the bundle of sacks on it,
it doesn't have to be משכה. meshacha. So רש"י Rashi says the
difference is why are you putting the bundle of sacks on it?
Are you putting the bundle of sacks on it because you actually
somehow want it to carry the sacks? Okay, you haven't actually maybe
it hasn't started walking, but you're planning on using it to carry
the sacks? Or is it basically like you're there and you're talking
to your friend and you need just to put it down for
a sec, but you're not planning on using it. It's not in
an עבודה avoda context. So בשעת עבודה be-sha'at avoda here certainly means
like an עבודה avoda context. Okay, so the way we're learning it
is as opposed to before where we conceptualized it as עבודה avoda
and it has to actually be acting and moving and using it,
here and then it would be the same definition by פרה. Para
If פרה has a stricter definition, even if the sacks go on
it without it carrying. carrying the sacks, we're basically saying it's אשר
לא עלה, Asher Lo Ala, you didn't put anything on it. The
only significance of the word עול ol is that if it's you
put something on it for the purpose of עבודה. Avoda. עול, Ol
if you put a yoke on it even not for the purpose
of עבודה, Avoda, I don't know why you'd put it on just
because we needed to rest your hands or something. Okay, that would
be the basic difference. But fundamentally it's much more about אשר לא
עלה Asher Lo Ala than it is about the concept of עבודה.
Avoda.
All right, so now it continues.
Okay, ואימא Ve-eima says
Moshe, ואימא אשר לא עלה עליה כלל או פרט כלל ופרט ואין
בכלל אלא מה שבפרט, Ve-eima Asher Lo Ala Aleha Klal O Prat
Klal U-Prat Ve-Ein Ba-Klal Ela Ma She-Ba-Prat, עול אם מידי אחריני לא.
Ol Im Midi Acharini Lo. If you're learning it out from not
from the גזירה שוה Gezeira Shava to עגלה, egla, but from the
words אשר לא עלה עליה עול, Asher Lo Ala Aleha Ol, let's
just say that it's only עול Ol, that עול Ol is the
פרט. Prat. So the גמרא Gemara says no, אשר ריבויה הוא. Asher
Ribuya Hu. אשר לא עלה עליה עול Asher Lo Ala Aleha Ol
didn't say לא עלה עליה עול. Lo Ala Aleha Ol. אשר asher
somehow is coming to broaden the, you know, range of things that
it would have done. I don't know how. Okay, ותניא נמי גבי
עגלה כי האי גוונא, Ve-Tanya Nami Gabi Egla Ki Hai Gavna, we
have a similar ברייתא Braita by עגלה. עול Ol אין לי אלא
עול ein li ela ol. שאר עבודות מנין? shear avodot minayin? And
by עגלה it says אשר לא משכה בעול, Asher Lo Mashcha Ba-Ol,
right? It didn't draw a yoke. How do I know if it
did other עבודות? Avodot? תלמוד לומר אשר לא עובד בה Talmud Lomar
Asher Lo Uvad Ba מכל מקום, Mi-Kol Makom, any עבודה. Avoda. אם
כן מה תלמוד לומר עול? Im Ken Ma Talmud Lomar Ol? So
what's the purpose of the yoke? עול פוסל בין בשעת עבודה ובין
שלא בשעת עבודה. Ol Posel Bein Be-She-at Avoda U-Bein She-lo Be-She-at Avoda.
The עול Ol whether you're, it's on for the purpose of doing
עבודה Avoda or not is a problem as long as I guess
it walks with it.
שאר עבודות אין פוסלות אלא בשעת עבודה She-ar Avodot Ein Poslot Ela
Be-She-at Avoda would only be a problem in the context of using
them for an עבודה. Avoda. Okay, ואימא אשר לא עובד בה כלל
או פרט כלל ופרט ואין בכלל אלא מה שבפרט Ve-eima Asher Lo
Uvad Ba Klal O Prat Klal U-Prat Ve-Ein Ba-Klal Ela Ma She-Ba-Prat
או אם מידי אחריני לא. O Im Midi Acharini Lo. Why don't
we do a כלל ופרט? Klal U-Prat? Of course this is a
harder כלל ופרט Klal U-Prat because this is different פסוקים, different phrases,
אשר לא עובד בה, Asher Lo Uvad Ba, אשר לא משכה בעול.
Asher Lo Mashcha Ba-Ol. This would be much harder to conflate to
be about an עול, Ol, but that's the question. אין
בכלל אלא מה שבפרט. Ein Ba-Klal Ela Ma She-Ba-Prat. So the
גמרא Gemara says
אשר ריבויה הוא. Asher Ribuya Hu. No, the word the next אשר
Asher is a ריבוי. Ribuy. But this clearly is much more of
a ריבוי Ribuy because this is a separate phrase. אשר לא עובד
בה Asher Lo Uvad Ba is one context, אשר לא משכה בעול
Asher Lo Mashcha Ba-Ol is a different. That אשר לא עלה עליה,
Asher Lo Ala Aleha, this is all the same phrase. So this
is a lot harder to understand how to say that we can
broaden it to include things that aren't an עול. Ol. But here
really you're dealing with two different phrases. Okay, אמר רבי אבהו. Amar
Rabbi Abbahu. So רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu said: בעי מיניה מרבי יוחנן.
Ba-i Minei Mi-Rabbi Yochanan. We asked from רבי יוחנן: Rabbi Yochanan: משיכת
עול בכמה? Meshichat Ol Be-Chama? When you say by the עגלה it
has to be משכה בעול, Mashcha Ba-Ol, it has to walk with
it, how far does it have to walk? Like one step?
So אמר
ליה: Amar Lei: כמלא עול, Ki-Mlo Ol, the length of a yoke
itself. That's משכה בעול, Mashcha Ba-Ol, like it moved the thing its
own, you know, it's displaced it its own space. So איבעיא להו:
Iba-ya Lehu: לאורכו או לרוחבו? Le-Orko O Le-Rochvo? The length of a
yoke or the width of a yoke? Okay, אמרו ליה ההוא מרבנן
ורבי יעקב שמיה. Amru Lei Hahu Me-Rabbanan Ve-Rabbi Yaakov Shemei. So one
of the rabbis, his name was Rabbi Yaakov, said: לדידי מפרשא לי
מיניה דרבי יוחנן. Le-Didi Mifarsha Li Minei De-Rabbi Yochanan. It was explained
to me from the name of רבי יוחנן: Rabbi Yochanan: משיכת עול
לרוחבו טפח. Meshichat Ol Le-Rochvo Tefach.
The drawing of a yoke for the עגלה ערופה Egla Arufa
goes by the width of the yoke which is a טפח. Tefach.
ולימא טפח. Ve-Leima Tefach. So just say it has to go a
טפח. Tefach. Why do you say it has to go the width
of a yoke? So קמשמע לן שיעורא דעול טפח Kamashma Lan Shi-ura
De-Ol Tefach to tell you that the width of a yoke is
a טפח. Tefach. Why do I need to know that? הוה למאי
נפקא מינה? Hava Le-Mai Nafka Mina? What do I care about a
טפח? Tefach? למקח וממכר. Le-Mikach U-Mimkar. For business. If I'm buying a
yoke and you deliver yokes that are less than a טפח Tefach
wide, I could say that that clearly does not qualify as a
yoke.
Or you could have just said that it's doing it for conceptually,
that the reason we say by a טפח Tefach is that's what
it means to be משוך, Mashuch, is to displace something its own
space. I don't get. You don't get.
I don't get. I have the tiniest.
What do you mean?
It's like width.
You know what a yoke looks like?
Yes, I do. I have several yokes at home.
Right or whatever. It's I don't know that's not a good drawing
but anyway. Right, here's here's the head of the cow. So the
width is this part. That part. That's the width. Okay. All right.
All right. So it says okay. אמר רבי יוחנן בן שאול. Amar
Rabbi Yochanan Ben Shaul. אמר רבי יוחנן בן שאול. Amar Rabbi Yochanan
Ben Shaul.
מפני מה אמרה תורה הביא עגלה בנחל? Mipnei Ma Amra Torah Hevi
Egla Be-Nachal? Why did the Torah say bring a calf in the
wadi? אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא: Amar Ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu: יבא דבר שלא
עשה פירות. Yavo Davar She-Lo Asa Peirot. Bring something that has never
produced fruit because it's also by the way that might also be
why עבודה Avoda is פוסל Posel by her. Not only
is it young and hasn't had children but it's never been used
for anything. It's innocent, it's, you know, untarnished. So that could be
the idea again specifically, right, עבודה Avoda is very distinctive here. It's
not by קרבנות. Korbanot. Okay, so something that has not produced
anything, ויערף, Ve-Ye-aref, and let it next be broken, במקום שאין עושה
פירות, Bi-Mekom She-Ein Oseh Peirot, in a place that doesn't produce anything.
Why?
ויכפר על מי שלא הניחו לעשות פירות Vi-Ychaper Al Mi She-Lo Hinichu
La-Asot Peirot and to atone for somebody who never had a chance
to produce fruit in this world. Somebody who he was who was
murdered, you know, maybe slain in their youth. So the גמרא Gemara
says, מאי פירות? mai peiros? Now what do we mean by פירות
peiros for the person who did not produce פירות? peiros? אילימא פריה
ורביה? Eilima pirya ve'rivya? If it means that he did not have
children, אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, זקן וסריס הכי נמי דלא עבדינן? zaken
vesaris hachi nami delo avdinan? Would you not do עגלה ערופה egla
arufa for somebody who couldn't have kids anyway? Right? Who was, let's
say, older, elderly—I mean, if he was elderly, maybe he did have
kids, but he was no longer able to have kids. Or somebody
that was sterile? Would you not do it? Because anyway that person
couldn't have done children, it wasn't the fact that he was murdered
that prevented that. So the גמרא says, אלא מצוות. ela mitzvot. No,
it means that he did not have the opportunity to do good
deeds, which again, interestingly, can tie into the idea of עובד בה,
uvad ba, right? That it was not worked. So it hadn't had
an opportunity to, this young calf hadn't had an opportunity to make
a mark in the world, to make a difference, to have its
labor and so on. And so somebody who had been slain, of
course, if somebody was slain at the end of their lives, they
might have done a lot of מצוות, mitzvot, right? They might have
had a lot of kids, but the point is, it still prevented
them from doing more. Okay, so I mean, obviously it doesn't match
up perfectly, but there still is that idea
of, right, of that wasted potential. Okay.
תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan,
our Rabbis taught. מנין לאיתן? Minayin le'eitan? אומר מורידין אותו לנחל איתן.
Omer moridin oto lenachal eitan. איתן כמשמעו קשה, Eitan kemashmao kashe, it
has to be hard rock.
מנין לאיתן שהוא קשה? Minayin le'eitan shehu kashe? היינו שנאמר—oh my God,
I have no idea how we're going to get through this. איתן
מושבך ושים בסלע קינך, Eitan moshavcha vesim basela kinecha. six minutes, we're
going to get to the bottom of the דף. daf. איתן eitan
מושבך ושים בסלע קינך. Okay, your dwelling place is strong in the
rocks. ואומר שמעו הרים את ריב ה׳ והאיתנים מוסדי ארץ. Ve'omer shim'u
harim et riv Hashem veha'eitanim mosdei aretz. Hear, ye mountains, the fight
of God and the strong ones, the foundations of the earth. אחרים
אומרים מנין לאיתן שהוא ישן? Acherim omrim minayin le'eitan shehu yashan? No,
איתן eitan means that it's ancient. So נחל איתן nachal eitan means
an ancient wadi. Or רש״י Rashi says it means that it has
never been, you know, the dirt has never been dug up. So
the ground goes back to like ancient times. שנאמר גוי איתן הוא,
Shene'emar goi eitan hu, it's a nation, it's an איתן nation. גוי
מעולם הוא, Goi me'olam hu, from, you know, from ancient times.
Okay. Now. וערפוהו שם בקופיץ מאחוריה, Ve'arfuha sham bekofitz me'achoreiha, with a
hatchet from behind. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? גמר עריפה עריפה מחטאת העוף.
Gmar arifa arifa mechatat ha'of. From חטאת chatat it says ומלק את
ראשו, umalak et rosho, you split its head with the finger, whatever,
from behind the neck, the nape of the neck. You do it
from behind. So here too עריפה means from the back. ומקומה אסור
מלזרוע ומלעבוד, Umekomah asur milizroa umila'avod, and you can't plant in the
place. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, אשר לא יעבד בה ולא יזרע. asher
lo ye'aved bah velo yizarei'a. So לשעבר, leshe'avar, which means in the
past. See רבי יאשיה. Rabbi Yoshiya. יאשיה Yoshiya means it means a
place that had not been worked and planted. It does not mean
shall not be worked and planted. רבי יונתן אומר להבא. Rabbi Yonatan
omer lehaba. No, it means shall, you're not allowed to use it
in the future to plant. רבא אמר להבא דכולי עלמא לא פליגי,
Rava amar lehaba dechulei alma lo peligi, דכתיב ולא
יזרע. dechtiv velo yizarei'a. Everybody agrees that you can't do it in
the future. ולא יזרע Velo yizarei'a means shall not
be seeded. כי פליגי לשעבר. Ki peligi leshe'avar. The question is whether
it means in the past it had never been used for that.
רבי יאשיה סבר מי כתיב ולא יועבד? Rabbi Yoshiya savar mi ktiv
velo yu'avad?
It doesn't say ולא יועבד, velo yu'avad, it says ולא יעבד, velo
ye'aved, which, I don't know, I'm not sure what the grammar is.
But anyway,
anyway, anyway for him ולא יעבד velo ye'aved
means that it's in the—that it refers to the past and not
just the future. לא יעבוד בה, Lo ya'avod bah, maybe, should have
been the future. רבי יונתן מי כתיב אשר לא נעבד? Rabbi Yonatan
mi ktiv asher lo ne'evad? Had it meant the past it would
have said נעבד. ne'evad. אשר לא יועבד Asher lo yu'avad means for
the future.
So maybe he's writing it out מלא, malei, you know, with
a ו. vav. Yeah, I still don't get it. ע-ב-ד Ayin-beit-dalet could
be יועבד. yu'avad.
Could be. רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya would say אשר לשעבר משמע. asher
leshe'avar mashma. No, that had not
been—אשר Asher means that had not been. If it says you may
not, it would say אל נחל איתן ולא יעבד בו ולא יזרע.
el nachal eitan velo ye'aved bo velo yizarei'a. You shall not work
it. אשר means had not been worked. Okay. רבי יונתן אשר ריבויא
הוא. Rabbi Yonatan asher ribuia hu. No, it's coming to be more
inclusive. I'm forgetting what it's including.
רש״י Rashi says—oh, that even if it's not planting, even other types
of עבודות avodot are also included. Okay, so everybody agrees according to
the גמרא that for the future you cannot work it. The question
is whether it's also saying that in the past it had not
been worked. ומותר לסרוק שם פשתן ולנקר שם אבנים. Umutar lisrok sham
pishtan ulenaker sham avanim. Now you can do things that don't use
the soil. You can use it there to, I don't know, clean
flax. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, אשר לא יעבד בו ולא יזרע. asher
lo ye'aved bo velo yizarei'a. אין לי אלא זריעה. Ein li ela
zri'ah. I only know that you can't plant. שאר עבודות מנין? She'ar
avodot minayin? And here's the ריבוי. ribui. How do I know you
can't do anything with the soil? תלמוד לומר אשר לא יעבד בו
מכל מקום. Talmud lomar asher lo ye'aved bo mikol makom. Can't do
anything. אם כן מה תלמוד לומר ולא יזרע? Im ken mah talmud
lomar velo yizarei'a? So why say plant? לומר לך מה זריעה מיוחדת
שהיא בגופה של קרקע, Lomar lach mah zri'ah meyuchadet shehi begufah shel
karka, because it's something, זריעה zri'ah is something that actually uses the
soil, אף כל שהיא בגופה של קרקע, af kol shehi begufah shel
karka, so anything that uses the soil you can't do. יצא סריקת
פשתן וניקור אבנים, Yatza srikas pishtan venikur avanim, as opposed to combing
flax and cleaning stones, שאינה בגופה של קרקע, she'eina begufah shel karka,
that's just standing on the ground, that you can do. ואימא אשר
לא יעבד בה כלל ולא יזרע פרט כלל ופרט אין בכלל אלא
מה שבפרט זריעה אין מידי אחרינא לא. Ve-eima asher lo ye-aved ba
klal velo yizarei prat klal uprat ein baklal ela ma she-baprat zeria
ein midei achrina lo. Since it's a כלל ופרט klal uprat and
it's just planting, seeding. No, אשר ריבויה הוא, Asher ribuya hu, that's
what we said before. אשר is coming to tell you that it
is, it is broader. It's not just planting. You can't do a
range of things like planting. You can't use the soil, but other
things you can do.
Now, זקני העיר רוחצים את ידיהם, Ziknei ha-ir rochatzim es yedeihen, the
elders washed their hands. תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan: וכל זקני העיר ההיא
הקרובים אל החלל ירחצו את ידיהם, Vechol ziknei ha-ir ha-hi hakerovim el
hachalal yirchatzu es yedeihen, they will wash their hands על העגלה הערופה
בנחל. al ha-egla ha-arufa banachal. מה תלמוד לומר הערופה? Ma talmud lomar
ha-arufa? Why did they have to say 'the one that was broken-necked'?
We already know that. מה תלמוד לומר הערופה? Ma talmud lomar ha-arufa?
על מקום עריפתה של עגלה, Al mekom arifasah shel egla, presumably the
water is spilled over the place where the neck was severed, like
they do it literally on top of the עגלה, on top of
where the neck was broken, where it was, where it was broken.
ואמרו ידינו לא שפכו את הדם הזה ועינינו לא ראו. Ve-amru yadeinu
lo shafchu es hadam haze ve-eineinu lo rau. וכי
על לבנו עלתה שבית דין שופכין דמים? Vechu al libenu alta she-beis
din shofchin damim? Did we think they're murderers? אלא לא בא לידינו
ופטרנוהו בלא מזונות ולא ראינוהו והנחנוהו בלא לויה. Ela lo ba leyadeinu
upatarnuhu belo mezonos velo re-inuhu vehinachnuhu belo levaya. We did not see
him and abandon him without giving him food and without giving him
accompaniment.
תניא, Tanya, now we're going to get into a whole little אגדתא,
agadata, דרשות derashos about the importance of accompaniment. הכי דריש רבי מאיר
אומר כופין ללויה. Hachi darish rabi meir omer kofin lilevaya. We force
people to accompany their guests, like it's such a mandate that if
you don't want to accompany your guest, I don't know, בית דין
would come to your home and force you to accompany your guest.
ששכר הלויה אין לו שיעור. She-sechar halevaya ein lo shiur. The merit
for accompaniment has no measure. שנאמר ויראו השומרים איש יוצא מן העיר.
Shene-emar vayiru hashomrim ish yotze min ha-ir. This is by, they saw
somebody going out of the city. ויאמרו לו הראנו נא את מבוא
העיר. Vayomeru lo hareinu na es mevo ha-ir. Tell us the way
to get into the city. ועשינו עמך חסד, Ve-asinu imcha chesed, and
we'll do with you a kindness. This is when they were conquering
one of the cities there in שופטים. Shoftim. וכתיב ויראם את מבוא
העיר. Uchsiv vayarem es mevo ha-ir.
He showed them the way into the city. ומה חסד עשו עמו?
Uma chesed asu imo? What did they do for him? שכל אותה
העיר הרגו לפי חרב. Shechol osa ha-ir hargu lefi charev. They wiped
out that entire city. ואותו האיש ומשפחתו שלחו. Ve-oso ha-ish umishpachto shilechu.
But they freed that person. וילך האיש ארץ החתים ויבן עיר ויקרא
שמה לוז. Vayelech ha-ish eretz hachitim vayiven ir vayikra shema luz. And
he went into the land of the Hitites and he built a
city and he called the name לוז. Luz. היא שמה עד היום.
Hi shema ad hayom. It's its name until today. So until today
we see, it's like a significant statement. So what does that mean?
It means עד היום הזה. ad hayom haze. תניא היא לוז שצובעין
בה תכלת. Tanya hi luz she-tzovim ba techeles. That's the city that
they make the תכלת techeles in it, they dye the תכלת. techeles.
היא לוז שבאה סנחריב ולא בלבלה. Hi luz she-ba sancheriv velo bilbelah.
Now, עד היום הזה ad hayom haze means it's never been disrupted.
So even when סנחריב Sancheriv came and upturned the entire world, that
city was left alone. ולא בלבלה נבוכדנצר ולא החריבה. Velo bilbelah nevuchadnetzar
velo hecherivah. When נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnetzar came, he didn't destroy it. ואף מלאך
המות אין לו רשות לעבור בה. Ve-af malach hamaves ein lo reshus
la-avor ba. Even the Angel of Death doesn't have entry into the
city of לוז. Luz. אלא זקנים שבה בזמן שדעתן קצה עליהן. Ela
zekenim she-ba bizman she-da-asan katza aleihen. But
the elders in that city, when they are getting weary of life,
they can't live, who wants to live forever? So what do they
do? הן יוצאין חוץ לחומה. Hen yotzin chutz lachoma. They have to
leave the city. ומתים. Umesim. And then they die. But in the
city, it's a magical city, nobody ever dies. Okay. So that's the
merit that this guy got for showing them the way into the
city. Now, the funny thing is that what he actually did was,
like, he betrayed his people. Exactly. I mean, the problem was that
he was a spy or a traitor or whatever, that he betrayed
whatever, he showed them the way to attack a city. But somehow
we are using this as a model of he helped them, he
accompanied them on their way. Their way happened to be into the
city, so he accompanied them on their way.
Okay. ובלשון קל וחומר. Uvelashon kal vachomer. ומה כנעני זה שלא דיבר
בפיו. Uma kena-ani ze shelo diber befiv. He just pointed, he didn't
even say, he said anything. ולא הלך ברגליו. Velo halach beraglav. He
didn't even walk. He just showed them.
גרם הצלה לו ולזרעו עד סוף כל הדורות. Garam hatzala lo ulezaro
ad sof kol hadoros. מי שעושה לויה ברגליו. Mi she-ose levaya beraglav.
Somebody that accompanies somebody and walks with their guests, to where they're
going or a little bit out of the house. על אחת כמה
וכמה. Al achas kama vechama. How much more so will they merit?
Now, במה הראה להם? Bame herah lahem? How did he show them
the way into the city? חזקיה אמר בפיו. Chizkiya amar befiv. Like
he just
pointed with his lips or something. He didn't even say anything, he
just indicated somehow with his mouth. איכא דאמרי בפיו איכא דאמרי להם.
Ika de-amri befiv ika de-amri lahem. He like,
I don't know, he frowned, like he tilted his mouth in a
certain way or something. רבי יוחנן אמר באצבעו הראה להם. Rabi yochanan
amar be-etzba-o herah lahem. He just pointed. Okay. I mean, it must
have been such a secret way if all you need to do
is just point, I don't know, maybe was a secret passage, I
don't know. תניא כוותיה דרבי יוחנן. Tanya kavashei de-rabi yochanan. We turn
like רבי יוחנן. Rabi Yochanan. בשביל שכנעני זה הראה באצבעו. Bishvil she-kena-ani
ze herah be-etzba-o. He just pointed with his finger. גרם הצלה לו
ולזרעו עד סוף כל הדורות. Garam hatzala lo ulezaro ad sof kol
hadoros. Okay. Let's just read a little bit more, because we've got
to kind of get a little bit further, we've got to go
fast. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי המהלך בדרך ואין לו לויה. Amar
rabi yehoshua ben levi hamalech baderech ve-ein lo levaya. If somebody is
going on the way and has nobody to accompany them. So right
now the, because the real point of accompaniment from the previous, from
the story of עגלה ערופה egla arufa is that you're walking alone
and nobody who knows the area is there to help you. It's
not just two versus one. It's like if you're a stranger, right,
you're more, you're more vulnerable for attack if somebody from the city
is with... with you, right, people keep their distance. So you hear
somebody is going alone and there's nobody there to accompany, okay, so
what do you do to protect yourself? So יעסוק בתורה Yasok BaTorah
שנאמר כי לוית חן הם לראשך. Shenemar ki livyat chen hem leroshacha.
They are an ornament of charm for your head, but it's obviously
a play on word of לויה, Levayah, right? They will accompany you,
the Torah will accompany you and that will protect you if somebody
else is not there to accompany you. וענקים לגרגרתך Vaanakim legargerotecha and
a necklace for your throat. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי Amar Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi בשביל ארבע פסיעות Bishvil arba pesiot שליוה פרעה לאברהם
Sheleiva Paroh leAvraham because Pharaoh took four steps to go with Avraham,
שנאמר ויצו עליו פרעה אנשים וישלחו אותו ואת אשתו ואת כל אשר
לו. Shenemar vayetzav alav Paroh anashim vayishalechu oto veet ishto veet kol
asher lo. So he commanded people to accompany Avraham. Now how do
we know only four steps? It sounded like maybe they accompanied him
all the way out, but it's sort of minimizing what he did
to show you the maximum benefit. Okay, so because he sent men
to accompany Avraham, נשתעבדו בבניו ארבע מאות שנה. Nishtabedu bevanav arba meot
shana. He was able to get the service of Avraham's descendants for
four hundred years, which is a funny dynamic because it's sort of
like saying if you help out your guest, you'll have power over
your guest, right? I mean it's like a weird type of a
way of speaking about the שכר ועונש. Sachar veonesh. He helped out
Avraham, so he had this power over Avraham. So I mean anyway,
שנאמר ועבדום ועינו אותם ארבע מאות שנה. Shenemar vaavadum veinu otam arba
meot shana. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav
המלווה את חברו ארבע אמות. Hamalveh et chavero arba amot. If you
just walk four amot with your neighbor, I mean you know somebody
who's like leaving the city or leaving your house,
בעיר אינו ניזוק. Bair eino nizok. So that then you do not,
you are not damaged. Now who's not damaged? You or him? Because
the real, it seems like you are not, that's your merit. But
the real purpose of the לויה Levayah is to help protect him.
But if you do that, then also you won't be. And again,
it could have some real benefit. I mean look, you know I
try to make a point of this, you know, when I have
somebody over for Shabbos, I really do this, like you know, you
don't just see them out at the door, you walk them from
the door, like you know, out of the house. It makes them
feel that they're being taken care of, they're not just being gotten
rid of, you know? And you walk with them, you know, just
four amot. But besides the sense of the feeling that somebody is
like doesn't want to leave me and wants to take care of
me and so on, you know, practically again, a stranger in a
city could be vulnerable for, you know, for people thinking that this
person nobody cares about him and is unprotected. So just walking even
a little distance sends like a signal to other people as well,
this person is my guest, you know, keep your hands off, like
you know. So therefore, so the merit for you doing that is
that you're not, you're not injured. Let's just read one more thing.
רבינא אלויה לרבא בר יצחק ארבע אמות בעיר. Ravina alveiya leRava bar
Yitzchak arba amot bair. He accompanied him four amot in the city.
מטא לידיה היזיקא ואישתזיב Mata lideih hezeika veishtaziv and then something happened
that sort of caused him injury and he was saved from it.
Okay, so I guess we will end with this and pick up
with this on Shabbos, but at least we're a good deal closer.
Not bad.